Evolution - A big lie? (brackets contain /transliteration and aux.information;) translation is intentionally close to the literal german narration; era: Bush-administration; author: lo sauer '04)
Good evening ladies and gentlemen. What we all saw yesterday,...
...shows once again how effective natural sciences are, at least when it comes to calculating planetary trajectories.
In the night sky, relatively easy to spot,
are the inner planets, Mercury and Venus,
- their orbit around the sun is slightly tilted-,..
..and yesterday a relatively rare constellation happened, with Venus moving across the corona of the sun -
an event, relatively well observable from earth. The whole scenario only took about six hours, yet here for us everything moves much faster, almost "in fast forward", taking just a few seconds.
The calculations were extremely accurate, another triumph for the natural-science-based model of the world.
But in science not everything is so unambiguous and clear cut.
For generations researchers have tried to solve
the question of how life came into existence.
Moasic pieces were therefore collected - the result was the theory of evolution.
Yet there are a group of people, especially in the USA, who'd like it all simpler and more homespun.
They don't believe in a complex developmental history for life, but rather they claim that there was an Intelligent Creator, who constructed everything at the shortest time - in the way we observe it nowadays.
Museums and theme parks are financed by them, to bring this idea to the public.
Here in San Diego, California, is such a center, and in the showcases history of development proceeds at frantic pace.
In a few days everything was finished.
Or here in this adventure park, demonstrated are how all animals and man, was somehow created in six days out of nothingness.
A fantastic and apparently catchy story about our origins.
Other than these creationists, the official Church copes well now with the findings of modern natural sciences.
It doesn't persist that the literal sense of the bible also equates to the physical state of the world.
The creationists instead try to establish, within a diffuse religious background, their simple view of the world...
...- and one could pass by it, if it weren't for the concurrent trend of the present American (Bush) government of adopting this (religious) for its educational policy.
Is this the way back into medieval times?
Firstly a glance at how natural scientists understand the formation of life.
Feeding and being fed upon. This battle shows the constant struggle of the chance to survive.
All possibilities are being exhausted, in order to find a niche allowing for ones own existence.
Successful at this, is the organism best adapted to its environment.
But with this (adapation) alone its survival isn't guaranteed forever, because the environment changes constantly.
Some animals have developed evermore effective possibilities to make it through this race.
Thus, this dragonfly occupies two habitats, - after her metamorphosis it leaves the water and conquers the sky.
And also the other organisms don't miss out on any chance (of preying).
This is the underlying cause for nature's diversity.
The creation of the richness of life proceeded over a long time.
Out of relatively simple organisms, over millions of years evermore complex organisms developed.
All living species nowadays are a result of this evolution.
Some had to change throughout evolution relatively little to adapt to ever-new conditions.
Others were subdued to gigantic upheaval.
So was man.
The development from an ape-like species to man is for us probably the most amazing process in evolution.
Significant restructuring of the hand and brain gave him the decisive ability to shape his own environment.
The path was now free for the next stage - the modern human.
And so our first direct ancestors, about 150.000 years ago, became a reality.
As unlikely as it seems, evolution is based on random changes and relentless assortment.
This rabbit species has found a way to cope with the change of the seasons.
In winter its fur color changes, it becomes white. Rabbits without this feature were easy prey, like this partridge...
...who because of its color which contrasts to the snow makes a distinctive target.
Predators lurk everywhere and see their chance of survival.
Like in this scene, the same thing happened to those rabbits who weren't able to adapt their fur color.
They died out. Evolution ran them over.
Winter-white-furred animals had a significant life advantage and could prevail till today.
On the entire earth, life had to meet this and other challenges.
Each landscape entails its own conditions.
As different as the land, as different are its inhabitants.
Some animals have succeeded in adapting to changing climate conditions, like this fox, which adapted by changing its shape.
Here with us, it shows in its familiar shape.
In ice and snow, in the polar region, this fox species has developed...
...completely different so, in the Sahara. The big ears serve for optimal heat exchange.
In the cold instead, a small surface is of advantage. All these adaptations are ultimately determined through our hereditary information within the cells - the genes.
In them lies encoded how the shape of the animals change "during" evolution.
In the example of the fly, researchers have tried to unravel the secret and see beyond evolution's game.
Hardly any other animal had subsequently been so intensively studied.
The fly developmental follows an exact plan.
Genes are switched on and off. Each body segment is passed along exactly the commands which are crucial for its development.
Researchers have identified the most significant genes for this process. (google: homeotic genes)
The surprise: only a few key genes control the whole process...
and this principle is found in all organisms in nature.
In these zebra fish (Brachydanio rerio) for example, the development seems to progress completely different from (the dev. in) insects.
But herein too lies a surprising finding. The same key genes like in flies (Drosophilidae)...
..are responsible in fish (Craniata) for the formation of their outer shape (morphogenesis).
A significant clue to a common origin of life on earth.
And also other animals have these comparable gene sequences - a universal tool kit of nature.
So it is possible to adapt to changing environmental conditions, from which completely different body shapes can develop.
An example for this comes from Madagascar.
In the genetic material of this Lemur, a baffling adaptation is reflected (/anchored).
What looks like a malformation, unravels as an elaborate tool in foraging.
The special finger assumes a similar functions as the woodpecker's beak and tongue.
With this finger, fat worms are sensed and its special shape allows fetching them out of the tree trunk.
A tidbit for the Lemur.
This were just a few of the mosaic puzzles which support the theory of evolution.
The basic idea is that, that the vast diversity of life on earth came about because animals had to adapt to constantly changing conditions and will have to do so in the future.
The possibilities of variation lie within the hereditary molecule. - the hereditary molecule itself is not constant and this in turn is the opportunity(chance) for evolution.
The hereditary molecule is changed for instance by radiation.
The hereditary molecule gets damaged, repairs in a different way - and in the process mutations occur, which are passed along in subsequent cell divisions.
These mutations can amount to all the advantage required to be successful in a certain environmental niche.
Or, also this drives the evolution forward: Sex. Besides the fun associated with it,..
..which gets us to perform this activity in the first place, ultimately different hereditary molecules, and thus different genes, merge.
And therefore new combinations come about which can mean new abilities for the resulting individual, letting it survive much better in a certain environment.
Sex therefore, the mingling of genes is one engine of evolution.
The theory of evolution is profoundly established, and since Darwin - since 150 years ago, legions of scientists are working meticulously on testing or supporting it.
And it is virtually unimaginable that in a modern society this established theory would have ever become hard-pressed, not indeed by objective scientific arguments but by political and religious movements (currents).
Is this the end of science? A glance into the fog of creationism...
Like this (scenes) it shall supposedly have happened on earth, when an ueber-entity, -a god-, created man and animal.
At least such is the imagination of  creationists.
Instead of a millions of years lasting developing process, man came about in just one single day.
And also other life forms have been created at breathtaking pace.
The diverse shape of insects for example, would therefore not have been a result of adaptation and selection, but rather like in a toolkit, a creator supposedly assembled the different components according to a fixed plan.
An Intelligent Designer creates the world.
This creationism finds ever more followers, especially here in the USA.
The literal quotes from the bible are supposed to (/shall) replace the biology education.
The creation-account shall, according to the faith of the creationists, represent a factually true portrayal of the formation of life and of the world itself.
Half of the Americans are strongly convinced that the theory of evolution is nonsense and Darwin a charlatan.
And so everything happened, if one believes the creationists...
Only 6000 years ago the earth came into being, as a ready, finished product.
Our planet looked pretty much the same as it does now, oceans, and mountains already existed
The geological processes shall have never occurred.
The mountains towered themselves up within the shortest of time, in total contrast to the insight of geological science....
the Alps didn't require millions of years of formation but merely a few hours.
In the world of creationists all animals were created at the same time...
...though some animals died out. There was a time where Dinosaurs were living together with giraffes(Giraffidae) and antelopes(Bovidae)
- This as well, against all of scientific knowledge.
Even humans shall have lived concurrently with the primordial giants.
The same motifs we know well from the Hollywood dream factory becomes an undisputable truth for creationists.
But the idyll didn't last forever and the sinful earth inhabitants shall have had to be punished by a devastating catastrophe.
According to the literal interpretation of the bible however, history succeeded in saving a couple of each animal (species).
The Ark-Noah shall even have provided shelter for Dinosaurs which have been taken on board as eggs.
Then came the Flood, relentlessly waging, and transforming (/changing) the surface of the earth forever.
Only due to the protection of the Ark, life could persevere (/continue).
Outside of the ship, everything was destroyed.
Creationists, thus interpret fossils - bone-discoveries from primordial times-, differently: as testimony of this catastrophe.
After the Flood the bones supposedly became petrified within 4000 years, by scientific concensus a process which takes at least 10.000 years, in most cases even way longer.
Dinosaur bones, virtually a testimony for evolution, are transformed (/changed) into witnesses of the Flood.
A hair-raising scenario which is ignoring all fundamental knowledge of geology and biology.
What is left, is a science-adversarial belief with the intend to anchor itself in the people's minds.
With neat songs, brain washing is carried out at an early age.(songs) like: “I don't believe in evolution - I know that the creationism is true”.
Manipulation instead of insight and empiricism - a state, we all thought to have left behind us long ago, but the pressure of creationists is not just increasing in the USA...
... but also in Europe. For instance, recently in Italy, and also in Germany, we encounter Creationists attempting to anchor their ideas in the scholary education system through books.
Some creationists are actually not talking about a god who created everything, but rather they talk about an Intelligent Designer.
...this is however nothing but a mere strategical ploy in order to become established within the educational system of the United States.
The theory of evolution is not doubted among scientists.
Surely there a few missing spots which are yet to be filled, - what this research and the building blocks of the theory of evolution looks like, can be seen in the following scenes.
The world 400 million years ago.
Here, a revolution happened with the formation (/development) of vertebrae.
Not the flashy underwater predators are cause for the change but a inconspicuous life form with leg-like extremities.
The fish(ichthyes) conquer the land.
A process which occurred relatively swift - it only took approx. 14 million years for the formation of amphibians....
...from which in turn, later on reptiles developed.
Geologists are fervently searching for remnants which document such decisive moments (in history).
A fish with feet would be (yet) another testament to the theory of evolution.
And this search was successful.
Fossil finds show that these intermediary steps did exists.
In this animal one can clearly recognize the new digits which allowed for the (first) step on land.
About the reason itself to leave water, one can only speculate.
The opening up of new food sources are the most likely explanation.
The development of the feet had far reaching consequences.
All land living vertebra still carry this heritage in their physique till today.
Fundamentally four extremities a part of their blueprint (Tetrapods).
Also birds possess the same skeleton layout (/pattern). They have conquered the air as their habitat.
Even in whales and dolphins the lower limbs are still conserved as tiny remnants (vestigials) within their body.
The development of the sea mammals does however contain even further surprises.
Killer whales (Orcinus orca) are a prime example for the functioning of evolution.
The killer whales are said to be the kings of the oceans.
A title which does not just pertain to their present day predatory behavior....
but also because their ancestors, many millions of years ago were wolf-like hunters.
An increasingly scarce habitat forced the animals back into water.
Gradually they adapted to the life in the sea and developed their typical appearance.
Today’s appearance of killer whales and dolphins hardly reveals (/lets one anticipate) the moving past of those animals.
At first glance their appearance equals perfectly those of fish...
...such as sharks. But there are many differences, in contrast to sharks these fish swim differently, - they wiggle through the water.
If one however examines the swimming movements of dolphins one will find remarkable parallels to those (motions) of land living animals, like the otter.
The swimming technique equals those of whales and dolphins.
Instead of wiggling through the water the forward movement is caused by lowering and raising of the entire body and by curving of the whole spine.
A method which has also proven of value for the movement on land.
This technique of the sea mammals has been upheld during their step back into water.
As such the swimming style of dolphins and killer whales is just one example of many, from which one can trace back the trail of evolution, even till today.
But there is an even more distinctive connection which ties together all living animals today.
The most distinct animals, the vast domain of plants and even bacteria display through one feature their common origin: their DNA.
- the hereditary molecule. Indifferent to the life forms in which the DNA is contained, it always exists out of the same four chemical building blocks.
Solely the sequence (/assembly) of those building blocks accounts for the differences in the life forms.
Even small changes in the genetic code can lead to enormous changes of the physique.
This was shown experimentally in crustaceans.
Modern genetics thus delivers the most important testimony for the theory of evolution.
It shows that throughout all life on earth, like a red thread, "stretches" only one single molecule: DNA
Out of the varied assembly of those building blocks the diversity of life formed.
According to the given environmental circumstances, life forms developed which could survive within the niches of our earth.
..and man too is ultimately a product of this evolution.
Baby: Baeeeh!
The way we picture the world is profoundly affected by the natural sciences...
...and ultimately our existence in our highly organized societies, on an overpopulated earth - depends on the very progress of those natural sciences.
If we fall back into mystical world views of past centuries then not only will our mental world impoverish but also our (/this) existence on earth will be threatened.
For this, we have a classical example, from the thirties and forties of the ex-Soviet Union, - during the Stalin era.
At that time, one man succeeded to completely re-function an entire scientific discipline, his name: Trofim Lysenko. (A man responsible for the demise of millions and suffering continuing to today!)
He negated at that time the emerging field of genetics, by following a motto on the lines of: place one sack of grain into the cold and yet all grains are chill resistant.
He let his scientific opponents be politically persecuted, or even liquidated and overturned a whole nation into misery.
The institutes for genetics in the Soviet Union have been taken over in the thirties by Trofim Lysenko.
He promised, as loyal party member, to breed novel, more productive sorts and in the process solve the nutritional problem in the Soviet Union
He claimed that changes in the form of environmental factors would be passed on congentially to the whole plant.
For plant breeding this meant the exposition of the crop to very cold temperatures.
If it would survive this shock therapy, also all its offspring would be hardened against chill.
Lysenko denied the existence of genes and chromosomes even though the international research efforts at that time clearly demonstrated this in evermore experiments.
The imagination of such easily imprintable new characteristics was in excellent accord (/matched) with the ideology of communism...
...for it was dreaming about the new human, which should be re-educated.
According to Lysenko the coming generations would now have internalized the ideals of communism and would pass them along to their progeny.
And Lysenko operated in accord with this scheme.
Stalin supported the fanatic party comrade, Lysenko.
Even though his scientific qualifications were doubtful, his propaganda was however efficient.
With promises which were in exact alignment with the party, and also meant a revolutionary abandonment of the capitalistic mindset of the west, he secured himself Stalin’s back.
Thus his ill-teachings became an integral part of all scholarly education and curricula.
Additionally Lysenko promised the paradise. All nutritional problems shall have been eliminated at once so long one followed his visions
Lysenko’s scientific opponents were denounced as public enemies.
The scientific elite of Russian gene research, which  at that time was leading worldwide, vanished into exile or was simply liquidated.
Even though Lysenko's ideas stood in stark contrast to all of secured scientific knowledge at that time, over the years the entirety of Soviet plant breeding was laid out that way.
The crops treated according to his methods, were propagated as the salvation out of starvation.
There was talk about new sorts, the doubling of the wool of sheep, and a tenfold increase of milk productivity in cows.
Plant breeding was carried out by obscure methods, the failures obfuscated, results faked and success stories made up.
As such for instance, chill-treated citrus fruits supposedly have been able to sprout in Siberia.
The reality looked different than the peachy promises.
The loss of culture plants were enormous, entire annual harvests were dropping out.
Bitter starvation was breaking out in the population.
Those failures didn't play any role however and were glossed over.
For 16 years Lysenko could keep his leading position.
A sad example of how an desperate ideological pseudo-doctrine, can make science into a farce.
Even to this day, Russian science is suffering from this literal exsanguination: it doesn't play any significant role in genetics anymore.
This is a traumatic example of the aftermath that entails when political goals try to influence scientific results.
If the creationists in the USA are making further grounds then the chance increases, that entire generations of pupils loose touch with modern natural sciences..
...or might even demonize them, and above all no longer collaborates in the expansion of human knowledge.
In other fields as well,  often observable is how politics influence science, for instance in the head-panels for stem cell research or energy strategies.
It begs to hope that the freedom of natural sciences is upheld and we don't fall back into the darkness of arbitrarily established world views...
...this was all for today, ...till next time, then...good evening!